Guide to the Honorable Company of College Printers Collection
Yale University Arts Library
Honorable Company of College Printers Collection
1936-1991
AOB 50
Yale University Arts Library
0.83
(2 boxes)
This collection gives a snapshot of the activities of the student group the Honorable Company of College Printers from the inception of the printing presses in residential colleges at Yale to the 1990s. The heyday of this group was in the mid 1950s to the early 1980s, when George Vaill was active.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transfer from various Yale University residential college print shops.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
The twelve residential colleges that make up Yale College have, in the past, each had their own printing facilities. The printing offices were started over a period of 40 years between 1937 and 1967. The Company of College Printers was founded in 1937 at the instigation of Clarence W. Mendell, then Master of Branford College. The group was made of Masters, faculty advisers, and undergraduate printers from the three colleges to first have printing offices. They met sporadically for dinners, lectures and discussions, and to print. The group did not become "Honorable" until Mr. Carl Lohmann so called them in 1940 on an invitation to an evening of printing activities. A history was written in 1965. According to this history, in 1952 George D. Vaill, '35, Director of the Branford College Press, was persuaded to accept appointment as "Historian pro-tem" of the Company and was charged with the task of preparing its official history. The history lists revival meetings in 1952, 1955, and 1962. The HCCP has existed sporadically since its inception.
Scope and Contents
This collection gives a snapshot of the activities of the student group the Honorable Company of College Printers from the inception of the printing presses in residential colleges at Yale to the 1990s. The heyday of this group was in the mid 1950s to the early 1980s, when George Vaill was active.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1955-1983. II. Honorable Company of College Printers (HCCP), 1936-1984. III. Lohmann Prize, 1973-1991. IV. Printed Materials, 1937-1972. V. Wayzgoose, 1952-1991.
Printing -- Connecticut; Letterpress printing; Vaill, George D.; Honorable Company of College Printers
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Letters to George D. Vaill, 1955-1983 undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Photocopy] Letters to George D. Vaill, 1955-1983 undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters from George D. Vaill, 1955-1975 undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Photocopy] Letters from George D. Vaill, 1955-1975 undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Honorable Company of College Printers (HCCP), Series II
  - Course syllabi and instructional materials
    - Apprenticeship course syllabi: The Berkeley Press, Spring 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - [Photocopy] Apprenticeship course syllabi: The Berkeley Press, Spring 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Apprentice course instructions: Trumbull College Press, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - [Photocopy] Apprentice course instructions: Trumbull College Press, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Inventory of equipment, Guidelines for use of press: J.E. College Press, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - [Photocopy] Inventory of equipment, Guidelines for use of press: J.E. College Press, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Membership information & printers and fellows lists
    - Certificates of membership and associate membership, April 18, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - [Photocopy] Certificates of membership and associate membership, April 18, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - College Press Printers, 1940-1945 1975-1992 undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - [Photocopy] College Press Printers, 1940-1945 1975-1992 undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - List of Fellows, Master Printers, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - [Photocopy] List of Fellows, Master Printers, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Publications and ephemera
    - Clippings: Newspaper articles, 1936-1937 1965 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - [Photocopy] Clippings: Newspaper articles, 1936-1937 1965 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - History: Addendum "An Incomplete History of the Printing Shops of the Member Colleges"; transcript of Yale Daily News article May 20, 1937, 1937 undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - [Photocopy] History: Addendum "An Incomplete History of the Printing Shops of the Member Colleges"; transcript of Yale Daily News article May 20, 1937, 1937 undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - History: "History of the Honorable Company of College Printers" by George D. Vaill, April 18, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - [Photocopy] History: "History of the Honorable Company of College Printers" by George D. Vaill, April 18, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Invitations and announcements, misc. items, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - [Photocopy] Invitations and announcements, 1963-1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Meeting agenda, minutes, 1956-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - [Photocopy] Meeting agenda, minutes, 1956-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Meeting notices, 1952-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - [Photocopy] Meeting notices, 1952-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1938 1988 undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - [Photocopy] Miscellaneous papers, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Stationary, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Random Notes on the Origin of the College Presses Together with a History of the Honorable Company of College Printers at Yale University," "Printing at Yale", 1967 undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - [Photocopy] "Random Notes on the Origin of the College Presses Together with a History of the Honorable Company of College Printers at Yale University," "Printing at Yale", 1967 undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Lohmann Prize, Series III
  - Invitations, meeting announcements, minutes, list of contributors, 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - [Photocopy] Invitations, meeting announcements, minutes, list of contributors, 1973-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Printed Material, Series IV
  - Pamphlets and small broadsides from various related presses, 1937-1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Wayzgoose, Series V
  - Wayzgoose invitations and keepsakes, 1952-1987 undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence and memos to members, minutes, 1956-1958 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - [Photocopy] Correspondence and memos to members, minutes, 1956-1958 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Invitations and member lists, 1963-1967 1991 undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - [Photocopy] Invitations and member lists, 1963-1967 1991 undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "The Wayzgoose" in Monotype Newsletter, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)